<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>USDA/NRCS - National Cartography &amp; Geospatial Center</origin><pubdate>20090204</pubdate><title>12-Digit Watershed Boundary Data 1:24,000 for EPA Region 2 and Surrounding States (NAT_HYDROLOGY.HUC12_NRCS_REG2)</title><pubinfo><pubplace>New York, NY</pubplace><publish>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 2</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://r2notes3.r02.epa.gov/Intranet/iOPM-ISB.nsf/allwebpages/4FF47DD3B3A5B1A885256DC8005C0DCB</onlink><onlink>Server=r2orany1.r02.epa.gov; Service=5151; Database=gisny102_r2oraNY1; User=spatialuser; password: spatialuser; Version=SDE.DEFAULT</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>12 digit Hydrologic Units (HUCs) for EPA Region 2 and surrounding states (Northeastern states, parts of the Great Lakes, Puerto Rico and the USVI) downloaded from the Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS) Geospatial Gateway and imported into the EPA Region 2 Oracle/SDE database.  This layer reflects 2009 updates to the national Watershed Boundary Database (WBD) that included new boundary data for New York and New Jersey.</abstract><purpose>This dataset is intended to be used as a tool for water-resource management and planning activities, particularly for site-specific and localized studies requiring a level of detail provided by large-scale map information.</purpose></descript><timeperd><current>Publication date</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2009</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>In work</progress><update>As needed</update></status><keywords><theme><themekt>Standard for Geospatial Dataset File Naming</themekt><themekey>Hydrologic Units, HUC, WBD</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>inlandWaters</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>EPA GIS Keyword Thesaurus</themekt><themekey>Environment</themekey><themekey>Water</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>User</themekt><themekey>EPAR2GIS</themekey><themekey>hydrologyEPAR2GIS</themekey><themekey>waterqualityEPAR2GIS</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>New Jersey</placekey><placekey>New York</placekey><placekey>Puerto Rico</placekey><placekey>Virgin Islands</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None.</accconst><useconst>The U.S. Department of Agriculture, Service Center Agencies should be acknowledged as the data source in products derived from these data.

This data set is not designed for use as a primary regulatory tool in permitting or citing decisions, but may be used as a reference source.  This information may be interpreted by organizations, agencies, units of government, or others based on needs; however, they are responsible for the appropriate application.  Federal, State, or local regulatory bodies are not to reassign to the Service Center Agencies any authority for the decisions that they make.  The Service Center Agencies will not perform any evaluations of these data for purposes related solely to State or local regulatory programs.

Photographic or digital enlargement of these data to scales greater than at which they were originally mapped can cause misinterpretation of the data.  Digital data files are periodically updated, and users are responsible for obtaining the latest version of the data.</useconst><secinfo><secsys>FIPS Pub 199</secsys><secclass>No Confidentiality</secclass><sechandl>Standard Technical Controls</sechandl></secinfo><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 2, GIS Team</cntorg><cntper>Harvey Simon</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>290 Broadway</address><address>2-PPE</address><city>New York</city><state>NY</state><postal>10007-1866</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(212) 637-3570</cntvoice><cntfax>(212) 637-5045</cntfax><cntemail>r2gisdata@epa.gov</cntemail><cntinst>http://www.epa.gov/region02/</cntinst></cntinfo></ptcontac><spdom><bounding><westbc>-86.138788</westbc><eastbc>-61.800370</eastbc><northbc>48.138692</northbc><southbc>17.443868</southbc></bounding></spdom></idinfo><dataqual><logic>Data are complete for the full geographic extent of the data.</logic><complete>Data were inspected for geometry errors and registration.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Compared to other data sources of similar scale and line work agreed well.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>NRCS State Offices</origin><pubdate>1999</pubdate><title>Watershed Boundary Data - Hydrologic Unit</title></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>24,000</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdate>200803</procdate><procdesc>The dataset was modified by the USDA-NRCS National Cartography &amp; Geospatial Center (NCGC) by creating a seamless dataset for the entire country for all 6 levels. NCGC has included attributes for hydrologic unit codes, hydrologic unit name, downstream hydrologic unit, man-made modifications to overland flow that alter the location of the HU boundary, and HU type for each hydrologic unit level 1-6.  NCGC has also added a square miles field to sub-basin.  An acres field already exists for each subwatershed.  The square miles and acres field was calculated in Albers Equal Area, NAD83 by NCGC.  At this time, not all records have attributes for all the fields, but may be filled in by the user for local projects or will be filled in at a later date. NCGC personnel have created 2 shapefiles from the national WBD.  One shapefile has attributes for 10 and 12-digit with polygons for the 12-digit HUs.  An accompanying line file showing the same linework with the three attribute fields is delivered with the polygon shapefile.  For a complete description of the attributes and processes used to delineate hydrologic units to 1:24,000 scale accuracy, please refer to document Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD) User Guide.</procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdate>20090203</procdate><procdesc>WBD data for Region 2 downloaded from NRCS Geospatial Data Gateway (http://datagateway.nrcs.usda.gov/)</procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdate>20090203</procdate><procdesc>Separate shapefiles merged and attributes for area in square miles, acres and hectares added.</procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdate>20090204</procdate><procdesc>Imported into Region 2 SDE database and metadata updated.</procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdate>20090204</procdate><procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Dataset copied.</procdesc><srcused>Server=r2orany1.r02.epa.gov; Service=5151; User=spatialuser; Version=SDE.DEFAULT</srcused><procdate>20120113</procdate><proctime>12221400</proctime></procstep></lineage></dataqual><eainfo><overview><eaover>Hydrologic Unit delineation are closed polygons that encompass all area draining toward the lowest point (called outlet or pour point) in the polygon. Because of nominal sizes for the different hydrologic unit level: Watershed (40,000 to 250,000 acres) and Sub-watershed (3,000 minimum, generally 10,000 to 40,000 acres), some polygons do not include all areas up to the drainage divide, but all areas are included up to one or more other upstream hydrologic units. A unique hydrologic unit code is used to identify each hydrologic unit. The hydrologic unit codes start with the 8-digit Sub-basin number that contains the Watershed. Likewise the Sub-watershed hydrologic unit codes start with the 10-digit Watershed number that contains the Sub-watershed. Each hydrologic unit has a unique hydrologic code.

The HUC_2 attribute is the 2-digit hydrologic unit code (HUC), or Level 1 Watershed Class, or Region.  the HU_2_NAME attribute holds the English name of the Region.
The HUC_4 attribute is the 4-digit HUC code, or Level 2 Watershed Class, or Sub-Region.  the HU_4_NAME attribute holds the English name of the Sub-Region.
The HUC_6 attribute is the 6-digit HUC code, or Level 3 Watershed Class, or Basin.  the HU_6_NAME attribute holds the English name of the Basin.
The HUC_8 attribute is the 8-digit HUC code, or Level 4 Watershed Class, or Sub-Basin.  the HU_8_NAME attribute holds the English name of the Sub-Basin.
The HUC_10 attribute is the 10-digit HUC code, or Level 5 Watershed Class, or Watershed.  the HU_10_NAME attribute holds the English name of the Watershed.
The HUC_12 attribute is the 12-digit HUC code, or Level 6 Watershed Class, or Sub-Watershed.  the HU_10_NAME attribute holds the English name of the Sub-Watershed.
The ACRES attribute is the area in acres of the Sub-Watershed, or 12-digit HUC.
The SQ_MILES attribute is the area in square miles of the Sub-Watershed, or 12-digit HUC.
The HU_121_STATE lists the states that contain all or a portion of the Sub-Watershed, or 12-digit HUC.
The FIPS_C attribute lists all the Federal Information Processing Standard state codes that contain all or a portion of the Sub-Watershed, or 12-digit HUC.

Detailed information about the attributes is available at http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/huc250k.html.
Also see the Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD) User Guide that was included with the NRCS data downloads:
http://r2quickplace1.r02.epa.gov/QuickPlace/r2gis/Main.nsf/h_BF292B758021F8A485256DDD00035325/A24E81F36BA9943A8525719B004DB0BF

Below are some useful reference information from the NRCS Water Body Database Users Guide:

Hydrologic Unit Levels

The six different levels of hydrologic units are shown below.

Hydrologic Unit  Level        Name                 Digits         Size                                           Units
1                                         Region               2             Average:177,560 square miles    21
 
2                                         Sub-region         4             Average: 16,800 square miles     222
 
3                                         Basin                  6            Average: 10,596 square miles     352
 
4                                         Sub-basin           8             Average: 703 square miles          2,149
 
5                                         Watershed        10           63-391 square miles                     22,000 (estimate)
                                                                                   (40,000-250,000 acres)
 
6                                         Sub-watershed   12          16-63 square miles                         160,000 (estimate)
                                                                                   (10,000-40,000 acres)
 
 
Naming the hydrologic units 

Hydrologic units are numbered sequentially beginning upstream and proceeding downstream within each HU.  For example, the uppermost end of the HU is coded 9908020301, the next HU downstream is 9908020302.

A sample numbering of hydrologic units:                                           Level

First 2 fields are the Region ------------------- 01                                         1

Next 2 fields are the Sub-region -------------- 0108                                    2

Next 2 fields are the Basin----------------------- 010802                               3

Next 2 fields are the Sub-basin ---------------- 01080204                           4

Next 2 fields are the Watershed--------------- 0108020401                       5

Next 2 fields are the Sub-watershed------------ 010802040101                 6

The numeric Hydrologic Unit Code is the primary, unique identifier for each hydrologic unit, however, the numeric identifier alone makes it difficult to relate a hydrologic unit to a geographic area.  Hydrologic units are usually named after significant or prominent hydrographic features in an area, however, hydrologic units are sometimes named after non-hydrographic features if better understood by the users and the public or if no hydrologic feature is named within the hydrologic unit.</eaover><eadetcit>Detailed information about the attributes is available from the Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD) User Guide (wbd_user_guide.doc) that is available with each gateway request.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><metainfo><metd>20090204</metd><metfrd>20130204</metfrd><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 2, GIS Team</cntorg><cntper>Harvey Simon</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>290 Broadway</address><address>2-PPE</address><city>New York</city><state>NY</state><postal>10007-1866</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(212) 637-3570</cntvoice><cntfax>(212) 637-5045</cntfax><cntemail>r2gisdata@epa.gov</cntemail><cntinst>http://www.epa.gov/region02/</cntinst></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><distinfo><resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc><distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the Environmental Protection Agency, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. It is strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data to evaluate data set limitations, restrictions or intended use. The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.these data to evaluate data set limitations, restrictions or intended use. The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 2, GIS Team</cntorg><cntper>Harvey Simon</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>290 Broadway</address><address>2-PPE</address><city>New York</city><state>NY</state><postal>10007-1866</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(212) 637-3570</cntvoice><cntfax>(212) 637-5045</cntfax><cntemail>r2gisdata@epa.gov</cntemail><cntinst>http://www.epa.gov/region02/</cntinst></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><mapproj><mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn><albers><stdparll>18.000000</stdparll><stdparll>42.000000</stdparll><longcm>-72.000000</longcm><latprjo>30.000000</latprjo><feast>0.000000</feast><fnorth>0.000000</fnorth></albers></mapproj><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><plandu>meters</plandu><coordrep><absres>0.000100</absres><ordres>0.000100</ordres></coordrep></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn><ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys><vertdef><altsys><altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc><altres>1.000000</altres></altsys></vertdef></spref><Esri><CreaDate>20180103</CreaDate><CreaTime>11254600</CreaTime><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><lineage><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files (x86)\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\Project" Date="20140811" Time="114744">Project HEP_WS_HUC12_WNassau_Diss "F:\GIS maps\BaseMaps\HEPboundary\HEP_WSArea\HEP_Scope_NAD83.shp" GEOGCS['GCS_North_American_1983',DATUM['D_North_American_1983',SPHEROID['GRS_1980',6378137.0,298.257222101]],PRIMEM['Greenwich',0.0],UNIT['Degree',0.0174532925199433]] # PROJCS['R2_Contiguous_Albers_Equal_Area_Conic',GEOGCS['GCS_North_American_1983',DATUM['D_North_American_1983',SPHEROID['GRS_1980',6378137.0,298.257222101]],PRIMEM['Greenwich',0.0],UNIT['Degree',0.0174532925199433]],PROJECTION['Albers'],PARAMETER['False_Easting',0.0],PARAMETER['False_Northing',0.0],PARAMETER['Central_Meridian',-72.0],PARAMETER['Standard_Parallel_1',18.0],PARAMETER['Standard_Parallel_2',42.0],PARAMETER['Latitude_Of_Origin',30.0],UNIT['Meter',1.0]]</Process></lineage></DataProperties></Esri></metadata>
